Finding Aid for Michigan Interfaith Council on Alcohol Problems records, 1933-2005
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Interfaith Council on Alcohol Problems records 1933-2005
Michigan Interfaith Council on Alcohol Problems.
4 linear feet
0710 Bj 2
Records of the Michigan Interfaith Council on Alcohol Problems and affiliated organizations. MICAP is a Lansing based organization dedicated to “solving the alcohol problem.” The series in the record group are: the Executive Director’s Files, Topical Files related to alcohol and gambling, Audits and Financial Information, Publications, and Board meetings.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
This record group was donated by the organization and came through Rev. Bill Amundsen, secretary (donor no. 9806 ) in November 2006. Additions have been received.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Interfaith Council on Alcohol Problems (MICAP) grew out of the Michigan state chapter of the Anti-Saloon League of America. The ASLA originated in 1883 as a non-partisan political organization which sought to pressure local, and eventually national, governments to ban liquor sales and traffic. The organization used local churches as galvanizing points for their mission and mobilized support by linking alcohol consumption with moral laxity.
The Michigan chapter of the organization was started in 1897 and had great success in urging Michigan's citizens and politicians to limit alcohol sales and legal consumption. The chapter sponsored legislation which would create a number of "dry counties" through the 1910s, and finally to put in place statewide Prohibition legislation in 1918, a full two years before Prohibition was required nationwide by the Eighteenth Amendment to the Constitution of the United States of America.
The Michigan Chapter continued to exert political pressure until 1942 when the Anti-Saloon League of Michigan dissolved and reformed as the Michigan Temperance Foundation, a name it retained until 1967 when it became the Michigan Council on Alcohol Problems and, finally, the Michigan Interfaith Council on Alcohol Problems. Throughout the latter quarter of the twentieth century the organization widened its scope to work against not just alcohol, but also gambling and drug use.
The Michigan Interfaith Council on Alcohol Problems was closely affiliated with a number of other, related organizations. These include the Michigan Alcohol Education Foundation, which became the Michigan Alcohol and Drug Information Foundation (MADIF) in 1971, and the Journal of Alcohol and Drug Information (JADE), as well as political action committees such as the Committee to Repeal Proposal E and other local PACs. These organizations ran out of the same office and were generally managed by the same group of staff and volunteers.
The MICAP record group contains material dating from as early as 1933, but the bulk of the collection is comprised of records from Rev. Allen B. Rice’s Executive Directorship 1972-1999. The collection has been divided into five series: Executive Director’s Files 1972-2005; Audits and Financial Information 1933-2000; Publications 1973-1999; Topical Files 1983-1991, and Board Meetings, 1974-1995.
Subjects:
Michigan Interfaith Council on Alcohol Problems.; Drug abuse--Michigan.; Drunk driving--Michigan.; Gambling--Government policy--Michigan.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-
Contributors:
Rice, Allen B.
- Executive Director's Files
  The first series, Executive Director's Files, contains records and correspondence generated by Rev. Rice during his tenure as MICAP's executive director. These files are primarily correspondence, though occasionally board meeting minutes, financial information, and newspaper clippings are also included. There are some significant gaps in the series. There are no executive files from 1979 to 1981, from 1985 to 1993. The 1998 file includes a significant amount of material related to the Committee to Repeal Proposal E (the legislation that allows non-Native American casino gambling in Michigan) of which Rev. Rice was the treasurer.
  - 1972-2005, 1 folders; 18 folders (Box 1)
- Audits and Financial Information
  The second series, Audits and Financial Information, contains primarily tax forms and professionally prepared yearly audit statements for MICAP and its affiliated organizations. The tax forms document the evolution of the organization starting in 1933 when the group was still the Anti-Saloon League of Michigan, and continue through its incarnation as the Michigan Temperance Foundation and finally MICAP. This series also includes financial summaries from the Michigan Alcohol Education Foundation, which became the Michigan Alcohol and Drug Information Foundation in 1971. Finally, this series includes a folder of miscellaneous financial holdings, which include items such as a mortgage taken out by MADIF.
  - Coalition to Repeal Proposal E 2000 (Box 2)
    (Proposal E allows non-Native American casino gambling in Michigan)
  - Tax Forms
    - Anti-Saloon League of Michigan 1933-1941 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Temperance Foundation 1942-1966 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Interfaith Council on Alcohol Problems (MICAP) 1969-1995, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan Alcohol Education Foundation (MAEF) 1955-1982, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan Alcohol and Drug Information Foundation (MADIF) 1983-1995, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Audits
    - Michigan Temperance Foundation 1959-1967 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Interfaith Council on Alcohol Problems (MICAP) 1968-1985, 4 folders (Box 2)
    - Michigan Alcohol Education Foundation (MAEF) 1959-1970 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Alcohol and Drug Information Foundation (MADIF) 1971-1985, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Financial Holdings 1976-1986 (Box 2)
- Publications
  The next series, Publications, is divided into two subseries. The first subseries is material published by the American Business Men's Research Foundation. They published the journal "Alcohol Abstracts" until 1976 when the organization moved to Michigan, began its affiliation with MICAP and changed the name of the journal to "The Bottom Line" (later, "The Bottom Line on Alcohol in America"). The other subseries in this series is MICAP's own publications, most notably its weekly newsletter, the "MICAP Recap," though it also includes the "Capitol Report" - a bulletin evaluating local politicians' stances on alcohol, drug, and gambling issues.
  - American Business Men's Research Foundation (Box 3)
    - Alcohol Abstracts, 1974-1976 (Box 3)
    - The Bottom Line, 1977-1987, 7 folders (Box 3)
  - Michigan Council on Alcohol Problems / Michigan Alcohol and Drug Information Foundation
    - Capitol Report, 1973-1983, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - MICAP Recap newsletter, 1977-1999, 18 folders (Box 3)
    - 1978 Progress Reports (both organizations) (Box 3)
    - Various other publications 1973-1983 (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files series is mostly comprised of clippings (primarily from the Lansing State Journal, Detroit News, and Detroit Free Press) on issues directly related to MICAP's mission and work such as gambling, underage drinking and drunk driving. These files also contain publications from other organizations such as Mothers Against Drunk Driving which expand on these themes.
  - Casinos/Gambling 1985-1991, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - MADD/International Reform Federation (Box 4)
  - State Lottery 1983-1991 (Box 4)
- Board meetings, annual reports, and related material
  The Board meetings series includes minutes of the executive board with some financial material and reports of activities.
  - 1974-1991, 12 volumes (in 2 expandable folders) (Box 4)
Related Material
The library also has in its printed collection the American Issue (Michigan Edition) published by the Anti-Saloon League of Michigan, 1909-1932.